all right greetings everyone
it is
september 9th 2022 it's the 15th meeting
for cohort one
and we are uh discussing chapter six
we're in the first of two discussions on
chapter six
of the textbook
we're going to go to the
questions
page and start there
where we have one question that we
explored a bit last week
in our welcome back
and then there's at least one question
prepared but anyone is welcome to add
more questions here
while we turn first to this question
what are the four steps in the recipe to
construct an active inference model
and can we make templates that
facilitate
people walking through some of these
stages
how much model building do people prefer
to be engaged in
in this
section of the textbook group
do people want to have one or more
model that they're personally developing
do they want those to be
scaffolded in a shared page to help
increment models along and see models
different stages yep brock and anyone
else
i just it it's the same problem as like
the first half of the textbook without
math it's not it's not going to go well
this half without modeling
it's not
it's it's going to be quite difficult i
think so um i think we should just get
uh that out of the way that it's yeah
it's not about whether you want to or
not or whatever if you if you if you
want to just understand it at a cursory
philosophical perhaps level then maybe
not but if you actually want to
understand it then yeah we are going to
have to model
something some way it doesn't have to be
the most complex most precise one but
yeah
i i wonder if there are if we could
develop like maybe a couple examples or
simple um
[Music]
ones that people might like to model
i don't know yeah
those are all going to be purely
agent-based but
thanks
i agree
i wanted to frame it as a question but i
agree with that
perspective
um
and following along
as we we um
[Music]
structure
a few specific cases
the rat and the teammates
the icicating
which are used in the textbook
then some of the examples that are used
recurrently in the literature
like birdsong and a few others
and for these many scripts
exist
and helping people who
[Music]
might not have the setup
either by with some walkthroughs okay
here's how you get octave running so you
can do this matlab script or here's the
standalone dem demo
because this textbook really only gives
the pointer to matlab
scripts and methods
like when they say um
that the standard schemes can be applied
they mean
a matlab script
and that's exactly what the step-by-step
guide model stream one
is built around
and
chapter seven
on modeling and discrete time
is going to
be
akin to the step-by-step guide
but it's not
um step by step by step by step
it's more like it takes two
bigger steps
um okay
how is this
four-step recipe
for active inference modeling similar or
different than approaches that people
have seen
for systems modeling from other
frameworks
for example in a reinforcement learning
[Music]
or cybernetic modeling so something more
recent and computational
or something more
pre-formal or computational
should this recipe be surprising to
people coming from a certain background
are there sub steps that are relevant to
consider brock yes
um
i don't have you know extensive
like formal modeling experience
but i
just necessarily kind of most of the
things that i've done for the last
half decade like entail some form of
this and i
don't see how you could
model anything without going through
these um
basic questions here like this is
it's a
bit
i don't see how this is specific or
um
exclusive or whatever to active
inference it's a bit
ambiguous to me how that yeah i mean
besides specifically degenerate model i
guess but
um
which system are we modeling another way
to ask that is what questions are we
trying to answer
um
or who
i think lyle brought this up like who's
the who are you making the model for
sort of thing
um
because the same like you were saying in
the
just earlier about
um
the particular choice of how you're
modeling it
uh
is just a choice on that system
and that has that entails you know
particular
uh
kind of
hidden states
marco blanket et cetera that um
may be relevant or may not be depending
on the questions you know what you're
trying to model um
but that that arises from those
questions i guess is what i'm
saying thank you ali
uh well
yeah
i just wanted to mention that um
referring back to your previous question
uh i also
i'm currently developing
a model and actually
an emotion perceiving agent uh
by
pretty much closely following those four
steps
but i'm getting some helps in that
regard and how to actually implement
those four steps in uh in my uh
particular situation
but um on the topic of modeling uh well
at a very basic level we can
um
categorize different approaches to
modeling um in terms of answering to two
to three different questions
uh the watt models the how models and
the y models
at least that's the kind of approach um
mostly done in neuroscientific modeling
so
uh in my opinion uh this these
four steps and this recipe
uh
can
be applied
mostly to
the how and the why
what models are
mostly a descriptive models of phenomena
so um
i think my connection
yeah you're about here
what models are mostly
yeah
mostly uh the descript descriptive
models uh and uh but
when we want to
uh model an agent uh a self-evidencing
agent which tries to um
which behaves as if
uh it
infers something about its environment
uh we have moved beyond uh just a
descriptive stage and we're dealing with
the how and
probably even the why questions there
thanks when i hear why i always think of
tim bergens four questions the four wise
aristotle's four y's
y
is a subjective
modelers
pluralistic playground
and it doesn't lend itself to one
specific even type of answer let alone a
framing or a specific parameter
combination
and i think that's a huge aspect of the
move from like
what are systems
to how am i going to model the system
which is a part of the turn that happens
when we start to model
is
we dispense with absolutism
all of a sudden these questions about
what we're trying to do
our preferences and affordances and
constraints
and limitations and everything come into
play
and we might make a portfolio of models
that are shining light on different
aspects of even the very same
phenomena
so it's kind of like an empirically
grounded pluralism and pragmatism
when we start to be engaged in real
useful modeling
and that is something that
i feel that one learns on the field
not necessarily
um
bystanding so that's just to say that
the modeling is really important
even for philosophical reasons
to say nothing of some of the things
that are coming to play in chapter seven
and beyond where it's like yeah the c
vector has this many
entries
because why
and how many rows and columns does this
have
but once we understand why the rows and
the columns and the shapes of these
different entities
are the way they are
then
we just have to use this scaffold to
think about certain
systems
consider their form
at a very structural level
like is it in discrete time or in
continuous time and so on
and then
we might set up
not just one generative model but again
families of them
in the future we hope and expect that
active block friends will facilitate us
doing parameter sweeps across families
of cognitive models and generative
models
um but even in this boutique
phase
of model construction that we're in
in current year
one would still say okay i want to have
one model where it's either acceptable
temperature or too hot and i want to
have one with a three-state model too
cold just right too hot here's going to
be a four stage model
and just being able to specify that
again instills pluralism through action
about how we're modeling a system
which is the philosophical point that it
seems like sometimes isn't
grasped
by those who don't engage
in the specific discussions around
modeling a system
um
okay
so
where does figure 6.1 come into play
a rehearsal
of some of the
figures we've seen earlier in the book
and many many other places
this is the particular partition
the particle is the internal and the
active sensory states so internal plus
blanket states equals particular states
those are the particles if we were
looking at dust under the microscope
like brownian motion was describing
initially the particles were the dust
particle
and then the external states were like
that which was not the dust particle
partitioning the generative process and
the generative model off from each other
we're dealing in bayesian mechanics
with particular states with particles
with things
that are able to engage in sensory motor
type
loops
this is just bringing in a few
uh more
pieces than that
which is just to call attention to the
direction and the existence of the
arrows
in
the work how particular is the free
energy principle of aguilera at all and
in follow-up work
there's discussion around
which
topologies
on this particular partition
facilitate or enable
which kinds of formal claims to be made
for example
one might find it kind of interesting
that sensory states have a bidirectional
arrow with external states
or might find it
equally interesting or differently
interesting or less interesting that
also active states
have
an arrow pointing back to internal
states
and
of course the questions that we
have raised all along the way of like
okay let's just say that we're gonna
model
a person's
arm what are the active states
what are the sensory states
what does it mean that there's a
bi-directional arrow connecting them
is this the only
topology for this particular partition
could we have the around the clock model
external states influencing sensory then
internal then active and just going
around the clock
without any crosstalk in the blanket
without any back arrows
is that
plausible
does that change the formalism
on one hand how could it not
change the formalism
when it's changing the structure of how
variables are related to each other
or maybe there are formalisms that are
actually abstracted away
from any
topology
choice
because what is being described
are the flows
and the gradients on
these variables
but then what are those variables
i think
i mean that just highlights this need
for for modeling but if we if we just
really briefly go back to that uh
one
um
it's like
the fact that there's this
bi-directional arrow between external
states and sensory states
is um
a bit confusing
um in that
again the language like
well if it is acting on the environment
isn't that an action state you know or
something like this um
in what way is it bidirectional so so
could you not draw that as two you know
one arrow going to the sensory state one
arrow from the sensory state to back to
the environment and then say
what functionally
does that entail
um and then you're you're doing this
particular selection
of of how you're modeling right
but i think you have to do that
um to understand why that is
bi-directional there
right um in that particular framing of
the generated process generate model
there right
um
which is
still to me also
slightly nebulous but uh i think
yeah just i the bi-directionality of it
between the action and sense states that
kind of makes sense almost um
that you sense your actions and your
actions or response to your sins but
that's not really what's being done
there precisely either right so
um
just explicating that is what yeah we
need to
separate and explicate what
yeah
another really important
question is like
this action perception loop is appealed
to
early and often it's the first picture
in the textbook
before the high road in the low road in
1.2
is one one
we're talking about
agents and they're interfacing with the
niche and we're going to end up calling
how we model asian degenerative model
and we're going to end up calling the
niche and the dynamics of a niche and
how it's influenced as the generative
process
and we're going to call the interface
between the generative model and
generative process markov blanket and
it's going to inherit this technical
definition from base graphs
and we're going to add these variables
and we're going to connect them a
certain way
but we're talking about the feedback
loop with the agent and the niche
oh
so what is this then
are the observations
the sensory states
and this isn't just like a a low-hanging
fruit like well then why isn't it like
um
you know why couldn't we call them
i mean they are called
as x and y
interestingly in the continuous time
formulation
and i get it that they're being
distinguished here
um
because this is the continuous time
pomdp and the um
discrete time pomdp
um but
where do we see
active states here
we see policies
so are active states along the branch
influencing
the b
matrix how the hidden states change
through time
so
there may be a very simple
um trail
from
this action perception loop
framing
to
the discrete and continuous time pomdps
yeah i think just to me the simple way
if you instead of thinking of this as a
circular thing where you're literally
going
from one state to the next state to the
way you might do in a normal state
machine if you're thinking of no the
active when you have an active state
that
however it is changing
that is necessarily entailing change in
the sensory external state and the
internal states
and and vice versa here with the sensory
states like
that if you if you perform some action
of some kind there's some active
change in that state like you're
necessarily
changing the internal hidden state
right
um
so like if you
uh
you know grab a
glass of water or something like this
like the what you're modeling
now has
changed
slightly right
and the sensors your internal states and
the sensory states
are doing the same thing where you know
for the glass of water or whatever was
this
you know
uh
object just sitting there
doing nothing but now
it's become a thing to to drink out of
and that's changed in some sense the
kind of external states that are being
fed into your sensory states right like
it it's changed
the markov blanket that you're kind of
selecting for or relating to
um
and i mean that
yeah the pumdp it's i mean i think that
is
visibly their you know do the same sort
of thing where
if you have
this observation you're necessarily
creating a
new internal you know or sense state
that is going to change your policy
selection so
and that's going to change your your
sense states
so
returning to the recipe one question
that i think
will reduce our uncertainty about as we
really do the modeling
is
um
how do we account for residuals
and understand which modeling residuals
which is to say
variability
in data that are not explained by the
model
which and what amounts of residuals are
acceptable
so if we're doing a linear regression
and the only data we had on hand was
height and the only data that we wanted
to predict were weight
then
we could just say we've used all the
data
and whether
the model fits um with an r value of 0.1
or 0.9
we know what the residual is
of
height on weight regression
and here's a number that describes what
fraction of the variability was
described
with this regression our value of one
being like it's all perfectly on a line
our value of zero being like it's just a
total scatter plot
we can say how much variability is
explained
and then
we're done with the empirical data that
we had so we can't explain any more
variability
when we're looking at empirical traces
of behavior
to
explain even a small fraction
of behavior for some systems
it might be the case that the generative
models already must be quite complex
in another scenario it might be the case
that a very simple
model
like
um
looks to the left are are uh
90 of the time followed by looking to
the right
i mean on average isn't that true
so then when we are evaluating models
whether in block prints sweeping across
models or just qualitatively or in a
boutique way
are we looking to reduce the residual
to zero
what traces of data are we looking to
explain variability in
and then if we're not going to be
with empirical traces of behavior
looking to reduce our
unexplained variance
what is going to be the criteria
by which we do model selection on
the aic and the bic
which are information criteria
balance
variability explained
across families of models
with their degree of parameterization
penalizing having more parameters
rewarding better explanations so seeking
to find a balance
with
models that are on the kind of pareto
frontier
of explanatory and simple
that's great that's like one extra
nuance on top of merely
explaining more variability with a
smaller residual
it also adds in the penalty for having
more parameters so that
um in theory and in practice
stops the modeler
from just okay well now we're going to
add in the temperature in this other
part of the world because one percent of
the variability just happened to be
explained so now we're just developing
these like totally spiraling looking for
more and more data sources to explain a
decreasing amount of variability that's
left
so it's good to pull back from that edge
through the use of information criteria
but at the core of the criterion is
still
the imperative to reduce the residual
to have a model that fits
within a model the way that we fine-tune
it
so that it fits data well but not
overfitting
and then across models we can see an
analogous process of wanting to model
structure
that fits without for example
overfitting or over-including parameters
um so i think one question
which might be added here is like
what data do we have
if we're doing a didactic model
and we just want to sketch it out and
run run a simulation and just purely
generate data
that might be useful in certain settings
but
the question of what behavioral data we
have is very non-trivial if we're going
to be approaching this as an empirical
analysis problem brock
just another question there um for
us what
uh what observations must we make or
something is the
related what data do we have
if you don't have the data that
there's if there's not sufficient
affordance information contained in the
data to model the problem then
do we have to model our action selection
at a second
or third
order
yeah exactly to find yeah to realize the
right epistemic value
okay
so that was figure six one
discrete and continuous
shallow deep and hierarchical
so just to
address this which might come up
shallow versus deep
is describing
how iterated
the
model is through time
within
one type of time
so you could have the one hour shallow
model
where hours are are units
or you could have the 10 hours where it
goes one two three four five six seven
eight nine ten or you could have a
hundred depth of a hundred with a time
click of one
or
one could have a hierarchical model
where there's 10 hours that make like a
deca hour
and then
there's 10 clicks of the deca hour
to reach
a planning horizon
of 100 time steps
so
deep is describing
within
one unit
or counter of time
how iterated
that counter is
depth is describing strict hierarchical
nesting
and so um they can both be used
separately or together
to describe
events over longer and longer time
horizons
crucially this is in the context of
language processing
the duration of the word transcends that
of any phoneme
and the sentence transcends that of any
word in the sequence
and
if we assume paragraphs are made of
multiple sentences
paragraphs always transcend and
encompass sentences so
anyone else want to just add up a point
i'm sure that you fellows are familiar
with this distinction but just wanted to
point it out since temporality in these
models
and doing model selection
on different forms of temporality
is going to be an essential piece of the
puzzle
yeah and it also reminds me of
the shankarian analysis theory
that if you remember
we talked about
uh earlier
uh and it's hierarchical i mean i mean
it's temporal hierarchy that
um
it tries to describe the whole musical
piece uh as a kind of hierarchical
layers
which i think maps perfectly into this
exam specific example of
language parsing
because that
also is a kind of thing that
should ideally
be modeled in a very
hierarchical way but the caveat here is
unlike language
which is
at least in some languages
are
necessarily hierarchical
music is
at least tonal music or
even non-tonal music
are not
necessarily
they don't necessarily have this
hierarchical structure so depending on
the kind of music or the genre of music
we might have uh either
a very shallow and non-hierarchical
structure or a very deep one
so uh that's something
that uh
i think
again refers back to uh the kind of
system we're trying to
model but even
that kind of system needs to be
more um
i mean
specified in a more granular
level
in order to have
an effective
modeling strategy there
thanks for bringing in that domain like
it makes me think of
[Music]
the intro the chorus the bridge the
verse
perhaps these are only in certain genre
of music but analogously and then the
measure transcends any beat in the
measure
with a special case of like a one one
time signature or something
and so on
and then
although language is described in a
strictly hierarchical sense
i'm wondering how syntax and grammar
actually create kind of a strange loop
for example it's trivial to say that
phonemes are nested within words and
sentences and so on
but what about the semantics of a
sentence that contains commas
and exceptions and then at the end the
speaker says the previous sentence is
not how you think it is
that
is also causing kind of like a deep
linguistic recall
that
can be trivially modeled as containing
nested units
but will a model
that narrowly considers
the semantics of words than the
semantics of clauses
how will it be able to address some of
these questions
here i think we can point to a really
excellent
attribute of the active inference
modeling framework
so
um
in this discussion where the lw paper
was cited
we could
just
marvel at nested systems and draw
blankets on blankets and so on and they
can be drawn around every organelle and
every little lipid granule in the
neurons and
or the brain regions and so
we discussed a little earlier like doing
structural model selection on which one
of those are relevant
however this does not mean we need to
attempt to model the entire brain to
develop meaningful
pragmatic
simulations of a single level
for example if we wanted to focus on
word processing we could address some
aspects without having to deal with
phoneme processes
this means we can treat inputs from
parts of the brain drawing inference
about phonemes as providing observations
from the perspective of word processing
areas so one could say i'm going to make
a figure 4.3
where s is the true word
and phonemes are being passed as
observations
to my word inference engine
and someone can say but aren't phonemes
the result of inference and someone can
say great
make that module
in block friends make that module
and pass me that data
and then we can do a nested model and we
can graft those models together
but
through the mark all blanket formalism
not even the whole markov blanket
bounding a specific particular entity
but just the trivial markov blanket that
exists insulating any two unconnected
nodes in a base graph
we can use that
broader
still technical concept of a markov
blanket
and just say all right
phoneme observations come in
and surely we could make a model where
another type of information comes in and
the inference is on phoneme and that's
what's passed out
so i
think again to point to this advantage
of active inference modeling
it allows us to
situate phenomena as complex multi-scale
nested systems
and also
bite off what we can chew
and makes it an empirical question
of how grafting together which different
structures might be useful
but we don't need to um
go all the way like turtles all the way
down
we can just say it's even if it were
turtles all the way down
we're modeling the third through the
fifth turtle
and the fifth turtle gets a top down
prior
and the third turtle gets sensory input
from one below it
and that's the part of the stack and
this is the lateral width
that we're modeling
another advantage of active inference
which not even saying this is a unique
advantage is that this goal directedness
and corollary capacities like
counter factuals on goals and the way
that counterfactuals on world states
influence our goal selection
nested goals
and transient goals or conditional goals
can be resolved
in an unfolding action perception loop
that's something that as this example
of like
wanting to enter an apartment
of being goal driven
over multiple time skills
and then being able to again zoom in so
it's like oh grab the keys okay well
here's the key grabbing module and
someone says well the key grabbing is
actually um accomplished through this
kind of grasping behavior
then that could be modeled or you can
just say we're subsuming
finger grasping kinetics
in the grasping module
because the phenomena that we're trying
to explain
and the data we have is just about when
things were grasped
or maybe the only observations we have
is when apartments were entered
so we can actually i expect
frame
systems extremely expansively
and clarify where we're doing formal
modeling
i think
maybe this is just a philosophical or
ontological framing of it but i'm
i don't see how you can model anything
well
without
admitting
that it is either
you know incomplete
or
partially consistent or
you know um but there is some hidden
state
which is probably not included in the
model
and to me active inference
kind of natively uh
has an affordance
at least at the very least a bookmark to
do that
um
and so
whatever
depth or hierarchy you model the system
um
it's okay
it's okay that there's still hidden
state and it's incomplete um if you know
if it sufficiently models answers the
question at hand then you can always
add another layer
or you know make the model more complex
and
that's just what we were going to do
anyways
nice
comment i totally agree with that
again thinking back to the linear model
example
um
where is that extra information
about like
um adjacent possibles for the model
it's unstructured
it's kind of like
either the structured information is
going to enter your linear regression
just so
and everything that's outside of your
linear regression
is um we're going to need to go back to
the square one
if we if we include a second observable
we're going to have to go to square one
and do the model selection all over
again and test for all the repeat
interactions again
um but in these multi-scale models that
we're discussing like you you said it
was a bookmark it's kind of a nice way
to
um frame it which is like the phonemes
you're bookmarking or
leaving an open usb port or something
any
thing that outputs a phoneme
will plug into that part of the model
anything
that
is able to hear
can be plugged in
to the frog riveting
anything that can see
can be plugged into the visual
component of the frog
and so
it's almost like
consistent with all of this
blanket talk
we're being clear about what is modeled
formally
and the borders
of the formal model
are degrees of freedom
as formulated
to be
expanded upon
and composed
one other
um
i'm not sure the context uh it's
something or ben ben gertz will say
attributed to um
pinch right but um
um that in circular mo um
circular reasoning
when your circle gets big enough it
becomes coherent
um
maybe another way of saying like that if
your model is insufficient
um
that if you
you know
add enough
states enough you know if you expand
your blanket enough eventually
if you're modeling something correctly i
guess uh you know it can
the general process can can
did match blanket states can can come
into
the line
nice
um some more active inference isms
so exteroceptive proprioceptive and
terraceptive
we're going to use active inference
modeling
memory attention anticipation planning
as inference
we're going to use active inference
that is what it looks like to integrate
disparate fields using one model
one family of models
so you know
others can work out some uh
fun ways to
communicate and frame it
but i think when people are like like
how is this simplifying when
it might feel like it's bringing in a
lot
or even stepping on namespaces that
people already have familiarity in like
we discussed earlier
you could ask how is memory related to
attention
or perhaps more saliently how will you
model how memory is related to attention
are you going to go on archive and just
look for neural network architectures
are you going to read
a book written before computers were
invented
and look at prose
are you going to dive into the
psychoanalytic tradition
or something that's maybe even
clinically biomedical
what's the move
and active inference addresses that
in these
um uh
theme of
where's the people used that mean
different things
for four hundred
we have
bayes optimal behavior
well then why do things go wrong
and there's multiple layers to unpack
first is going wrong
is about your
perspective on how the system perhaps
how you prefer it to be or how you
expected it to be
but like given where
you put the
dish
when it fell off the table
that was just compatible with gravity
so it was finding its optimal position
and fragmentation
where you placed it
the ball rolled downhill
as a consequence of where it was placed
and the slope it was on
and
framing behavior
in that light
we're modeling behavior as rolling to
the bottom of a bowl
what's the bowl what's the ball those
are the questions
but it's like chemical reactions
proceeding under gibbs free energy
minimization
when we have policy selection
driven by
variational and expected free energy
minimization
but how can things that go wrong be
optimal
well
it has to do with
different parameters in the model
given how they are
the model performs optimally
that doesn't mean computationally
efficiently
it doesn't mean adequately
doesn't mean it satisfies
but it may be framed as bayes optimal
fixed
and learned behaviors
this is going to come into play
in chapter seven
there's an amazing continuity
in theory and
in simple examples
with perception and learning
which is to say that perception happens
over faster time scales or perceptive
like processes happen over faster time
scales while learning like processes
happen over slower time scales
or even just
more generally
perception and learning refer to
parametric update processes
and you might even be able to situate
the same example both ways like if we
see a ball move across our visual field
are we perceiving the location of the
ball
are we inferring the location of the
ball or are we updating and learning
our position of the ball
for those with a computational
background learning
often equates to parameter updating
and so in that sense any kind of
dynamical perception is learning
so
for some backgrounds
the difference between perception and
learning
will be seamless
for other backgrounds
those are going to sound like totally
different processes i mean isn't
perception when you see the book but
then learning is like
when you understand something about the
book
um
and then speaking from a more
modeling perspective here
a fixed model
or fixing a parameter of a model
reduces the model's complexity immensely
or another way to say it
taking a fixed parameter and making it
learnable
introduces multiple
hyper parameters
and there's no single way
to address parameter learning
you could say well we're taking we're
doing moving average learning like a
column filter or just a simple sliding
window we're taking the average of the
last three
but now you have to parameter sweep
across how many
and with a single trial of data
there may be um
it may not be clear
which learning strategy is implemented
because especially if we want to
differentiate learning strategies
empirically
we would want to see like multiple
comparable trajectories
within and amongst individuals
in similar and different contexts
but now
you know our lab has gotten quite big
and we're doing quite large model
selections
even for
learning and updating
parameters that might just
conversationally seem really simple
like preferences being updated
so here's
this description of when it comes to
inference and perception as being fast
changes and learning as slower changes
though they're being modeled in a really
analogous way
it is worth noting in this book we
exemplify rather simple generative
models that are defined using tabular
methods eg with explicit matrices or
tensors for priors and likelihoods
in small state spaces
in comparison more sophisticated gms
are being developed in machine learning
deep learning robotics etc
so is active inference deep learning
okay
good fellow generative adversarial
networks
but
with uh bengio
and mirza but
are we saying those are formally active
inference systems
or are we just saying that
we can
think of it like birdsong conceptually
and then are we just
adding a rapper or a descriptor to the
gans
that our non-active colleagues are
building
is it shining any new epistemic or
pragmatic light on gans
i mean here's a whole paragraph on gans
home is behind
oh that's chapter 10. it's like what
happened
but there's still a whole paragraph on
gans
did you see that
how did that happen
whoa
i'm not sure what the optimal way to
view a pdf is or that one exists but
i don't think it's a browser
it's not bad but it's not
not optimal um
yeah yeah i don't i would i interested
in that you know
this
again the generative model
oh i know what those are so general
model like um and how you know specific
specifically
gans here and active inference like is
one
is the
rectangle a square
uh sorry square rectangle rectangle not
a square here is that you know what
we're is being said or is there a
you know
uh
yeah
degreed uh a um indexed blanket here of
a varying degree
um yep
yep
as far as i know and also you
fellows might know like
this is being pointed to
variational auto encoders
and variational bayesian inference
are directly implicated
as potentially recursive cortical
networks are
and world models
but
if these bridges can be made
solid
like you said with squares and
rectangles
so that we can say all sum or none
of
x are y
or here's how you project this model to
that
model it's going to just
like
break a dam
with
possibly certain applications of active
any final comments on six
and uh i think
certainly by um two weeks from now
uh
let's uh
look at the spm
implementation and look at some of those
that are pointed towards in the book as
well as some of like the epistemic
chaining
and um
pi mdp type models as well as anything
that anyone else builds so any final
comments
uh yeah i just wanted to point out uh
the recent
work by uh feels at all especially
uh one
the two papers that
person was also
as a co-author
uh is
one of the their main objectives is to
cross uh that bridge between active
inference and bae
uh via the cccd system so
uh that
bridge they're talking about in this
book is already been investigated uh to
be uh filled so
yeah they're
uh pretty interesting developments going
uh in that regard
okay any last notes before i stopped
recording
what is that paper
i'll send you the link from the discord
i forgot
um maybe just one
i don't know
uh
we haven't
tried to make a effort on the code to
like um
lay down some
basic examples from one you know the
first half but um should there be some
um
if we're gonna model stuff is should we
have a
subpage for that or do put something
somewhere in the coda for that i don't
know
we've had this code section from the
beginning
yeah and just
however
it should be totally modifiable
full control so
however this and anything subpages need
to be modified
and the github link
to
a textbook
anything that people suggest just let us
know
anything else
okay